We do have a lot of people in the waiting,
waiting in the lobby.
So we're letting people on in at this
moment.
We'll give people just another minute or
two to for the program to get everybody
on in.
Thank you everybody for joining us today.
This is the Training and Education
Committee meeting from the Medical
Psilocybin Advisory Board.
My name is Doctor Dominic Zerlow and I'm
the director for the Center for Medical
Cannabis and Psilocybin.
My role here is just to help facilitate
and to provide updates.
And today the chair, well, not just today,
but for long standing,
the chair is Brenda Burgard.
And so just as a reminder to everyone,
this meeting is being recorded.
So Please remember to use appropriate
language.
I will put into the chat a couple of
reminders and contact information.
And with that,
I'll turn it on over to you, Brenda.
Wow, thank you, Dominic.
So hey, welcome everybody.
Thank you for coming to the training and
education part for the psilocybin medical
program here for the DoH.
Really appreciate you all being here.
To save a little time,
we're not going to do formal
introductions.
So we're going to,
I'm going to read off the agenda here.
If Jorge can bring that up,
that would be great.
And then we're I'll introduce Catherine
Warnock with her presentation and then
spare a couple of maybe 1520 minutes to
take questions afterwards.
If,
if for some reason we're going through
this very quickly today,
it's because I want to give Catherine
plenty of time to present.
So in today's meeting in the agenda,
I'm Brenda Burgard again of I'm the
Chairperson for Education and Training
for the Department of Health.
And so to begin the core New Mexico
competencies and I'll just read through
everything here for fast track for
licensed,
trained and certified practitioners
participating in Indigenous Healers
Supervisors Co facilities to be allowed
to practice and after meeting standards
and completing New Mexico program and
those who are currently in training in
other states.
So in other words,
what that means if you are in some kind
of training in other states, you'll be,
you'll be able to take a little bit of
extra training here in New Mexico to
fulfill the core competencies that we are
requiring here in New Mexico.
OK to begin training and certification
structure.
The framework includes teaching or
supervising supervision competencies to
be a teacher,
not just a facilitator and a 10 hour
reciprocity track previously trained
professionals and we I added this in as
optional add on practicum refresher that
meaning that those of us who have not
been practicing but just need a refresher
course.
This is to be added on.
If you wanted to do actually practicum
and also to the education part,
which would be about 10 hours.
This is just this is flexible.
This is not written in stone.
I just wanted to add that.
OK,
so there'll be an optional supervisor
pathway with advanced competencies and
overnight and evaluation.
I put a question mark here of hours and
training program start to finish.
So if you're brand new to all of this,
we haven't really come to a decision on
how many hours this will take in order
for you to be licensed in, in,
in practicing psilocybin.
So without prior training and or
certification, I'm thinking of 2 levels.
This is all up for discussion of
combining didactic education and
supervision practicum and align it with
other full course programs in the US.
If there's time later in the the meeting,
we we will discuss this.
Otherwise we'll push it to the next
meeting if we have time.
OK, next scroll up please.
OK.
This is just a little diagram here.
In the first bubble,
we have meeting standards set by the DoH
and then from moving to the right is
legacy training and education.
Down there in the bottom is licensing and
Crick Cricket certification.
And then we have the medical training and
education,
and then we have the core competencies
and reciprocity next.
OK,
the core competency framework for medical
psilocybin training and education in New
Mexico.
OK.
The purpose,
This framework establishes the minimum
competencies required for safe,
ethical and effective practice and
regulate regulated medical psilocybin
program in New Mexico.
It is designed to support facilitator
licensing must be resident of New Mexico
clinical service delivery training
program accreditation and possible
considerations.
The CIS and naropa maps Fluence training
ipi intertrec synaptic institute prodi
anyato de vegetal Santo domini hope I'm
pronouncing that right.
Tribal consultation required for those
Theresville Imperial College London
Center for Psychedelic Research since
this, the Institute and the BA result.
Now these are just some of the many, many,
many places that are that we may consider
for the program here in the Department of
Health to incorporate here in New Mexico.
Because there are people from all over
walks of life here in New Mexico that
have trained in other countries as well.
So I wanted to also include that into
what we're trying going to present here.
The next is public safety,
safety and ethical integrity.
Public safety, I cannot stress enough,
in the last meeting with Knott's meeting,
this was one of the main things that we
were discussing at length.
And it, it's,
it's paramount to everything because
safety is what we're,
we're trying to really get everybody to
understand what that means.
And there's a whole there's a whole bunch
of things that go with this integration
with behavioral health systems in New
Mexico's the the next one.
OK,
the New Mexico psilocybin reciprocity
competency tract for out of state
certified licensed professional.
However,
they will need to be residents of New
Mexico in order to be part of the
licensing.
The purpose in this tract provides
streamlined pathway 10 hours plus for
professionals already trained in
psychedelic facilitation or related
fields to meet New Mexico specific
requirements including state regulatory
compliance,
cultural humility in New Mexico
communities,
legacy and lineage and reciprocity,
integration,
ethical and scope of practice alignment,
safety and risk alignment,
eligible applicants,
licensed mental health professionals,
LPCCLCSWLMFT, etcetera.
This falls under the umbrella of
practitioners who are therapists,
medical providers, MDDO&PPARN,
etcetera.
Certified psychedelic facilitators who
have trained from other states,
Oregon and Colorado are residents of New
Mexico,
Pastoral of spiritual care providers,
indigenous traditional practitioners with
pathway recognition and flexibility.
And I forgot to add,
end of life practitioners as well.
OK, let's move on to the next, OK,
Teaching or supervision.
Competency to be a teacher,
not just a facilitator.
Expect experience in clinical supervision,
adult education and training delivery.
Ability to access, assess, I'm sorry,
competencies for DoH approval.
Documenting psychedelic related training
plus hours.
Building curriculum, Teaching experience,
demonstrating cultural Indigenous
collaboration.
Engaging with the DoH advisory process.
A DoH approved training program with a
curriculum aligned to state competencies,
safety protocols,
and supervised practicum model.
Programs must have approved curriculum.
Instructors are tied to program approval,
not just individual credential,
a recognized professional or traditional
credential,
formal psychedelic training and practicum,
real facilitation experience,
teaching supervision skills,
trauma informed ethical competencies,
cultural Indigenous awareness and
affiliation with the DoH approved program.
Next.
OK,
so I set these up in into modules and I
want to encourage you all if you need to
go ahead and put questions in your text
and we can at least hold that until we
can towards the end of the meeting.
So, you know, I know that, you know,
I'm trying to create a flow here,
but I can't walk and chew gum and ride a,
you know, bicycle all at the same time.
So module one,
New Mexico legal and regulatory alignment
and we're looking at two hours there and
the content.
The New Mexico Department of Health
psilocybin rules scope of practice
distinctions,
facilitator versus clinical provider
documentation and compliance with
expectations,
mandatory reporting laws and competencies
demonstrates understanding of the New
Mexico specific legal requirements and
aligns existing practice with state scope
of practice.
OK Module 2 is legacy lineage and
reciprocity.
Reciprocity New Mexico focused hours or
or three hours And again,
these are just trying to get an idea of
how many hours these will take,
give and take.
OK,
We need to have historical lineage of
psilocybin use.
Ethical considerations in modern practice.
Impacts of colonization and prohibition
includes Maria Sabina and our Gordon
Watson.
What happened there?
The war on drugs.
We all know what that is and anything
else that may be part of this content of
the history.
Applied competent development of
refinement of reciprocity plan including
community reinvestment,
access equity strategies,
ethical representations of services,
competencies,
demonstrate cultural grounding and a non
extractive practice and articulates
personal and professional accountability.
Module 3.
Cultural humility in New Mexico
communities.
The Wizard 2 Content working with tribal
and Pueblo communities, Hispano,
Chicano populations,
rural and under underserved populations.
Language, trust and access to barriers.
Competencies.
Adapt care to local cultural context and
demonstrate humility versus assumed
competencies.
Let's roll up a little bit more and then
we have a workforce pathways.
I can't say it, you all know what I mean.
For Native practitioners to support
equity and inclusion.
Creative,
alternative or parallel certification
pathways for Native practitioners develop
in collaboration with tribal governments.
Allow for recognition of lived experience
and traditional knowledge when
voluntarily shared.
Flexible training structures for tribal
communities.
Ensure participant in an opt in or not
assumed or required.
OK Module 4.
OK ethics boundaries and scope of
alignment.
OK hours or two.
Now, I know ethics is a big one,
so we may have to add more hours to this.
I'm not sure yet.
But you know,
ethics is always one of the biggest
things that us clinicians need to take at
least,
I believe 12 hours within a A2 year time
limit for that so we can get our CE us
for that.
So we're always doing ethics as far as
that's concerned.
So the content for that would be New
Mexico specific ethical expectations,
scope clarity across disciplines,
clinical versus facilitator versus
spiritual roles.
That's pretty important.
Power dynamics and client safety
competencies,
maintains appropriate boundaries,
avoid scope drift or role confusion.
So we have to know what our roles are and
not have that blended to, you know,
too much because then we're,
we're hitting into ethics and,
and boundaries there.
So those need to be very structured.
OK,
Module 5 safety and risk alignment
bridging module hours are 1.
So I know this is probably going to be
more than just one hour, but I for,
you know,
reasons for keeping the time limit on
things during these meetings.
We can always add or subtract more hours.
The content here is New Mexico safety
expectations, risk response protocols,
referral networks within New Mexico.
So that's a really important one.
I think what we're going to be looking at.
Do we really need referrals from,
you know,
physicians or is this going to be what we
presently have right now?
This is a possibility.
I know as a practitioner I am,
I need to give referrals to psychiatrist
to give,
you know prescribed medicines and to also
do assessments as well.
So we'll we'll look at that more closely
as time goes on.
So let's see the competencies for that
aligns prior to training with Mexico
safety standards.
OK.
Now Module 6,
the practicum or weekend refresher
optional, that's 6 to 8 hours.
So that's going to take up a big chunk of
our weekends.
However,
I feel that the practicum is where we do
a refresher because some of us have not
been practicing for a while or have not
really had the opportunity.
So that is one of those things where I
think it needs further discussion and I
think let's roll down further.
OK,
Now here's a supervision track that I
decided to put in here because I think
supervision is one of those things that
we really need to look at as well.
Who,
who will be qualifying as a supervisor.
So advance reciprocity for supervisors.
An additional 6 hours.
Module A will clinical and ethical
supervision in psychedelic care.
Ours are two supervision models.
Evaluating competency and readiness,
managing ethical violations.
Module B,
advanced legacy and power dynamics.
Let's see, that would be two hours.
Navigating authority and Fluence and
preventing exploitation and misconduct
and accountability and structures.
Module C evaluation and gatekeeping.
That's two hours.
Competency assessment tools,
documentation,
reporting and remediation processes.
Supervisor competencies.
Demonstrates ability to assess
facilitators readiness and applies
ethical oversight and accountability.
Integrates legacy and reciprocity into
supervision according to the New Mexico
DoH.
And I don't know if there's more,
some more there.
I think that's it.
That's the end.
And what I found in in Dan's meeting this
morning is that, OK,
we're going to have some,
I'm going to use his language, you know,
parking spots for some of these things.
And also too,
if there's any have been any blind spots
and some of these that we can also put
into the education and training part.
So now all of that has been said,
I encourage you to put it in the chat if
you have any questions.
However,
we're going to hold that for the end here
because I don't want to take up too much
time here.
So, Catherine, Miss Warnock,
Are you ready to present your PowerPoint?
Yes,
I still need to share my screen so I can
figure that part out here.
OK, let's give you a few minutes.
Take a breath.
And while Catherine is doing that,
just so everybody knows,
I have put into the chat that all of that
information that Brenda had just read
through after the photo, for some reason,
I can't get the photo to copy into the
chat.
So,
but that way you can see what the
different competencies and the timeline
on that that Brenda was reading off, OK.
And Catherine, if you can't do the share,
I can share it for you and you can just
tell me when to go to the next slide.
Do you want to do that?
Let me see if I can.
I'm trying one more thing.
If I can't make that work.
OK, let's try it.
Let's see.
Are you able to see this?
Yes, there it is.
Excellent.
OK.
Well, hello everybody.
Let me turn my camera on.
There we go.
Hello.
So today I'm going to be talking
essentially about developing a safe and
effective psilocybin facilitator training
here in New Mexico.
I'm really grateful for the opportunity
to present today.
I was asked to do so mostly because I
have been offering training already in
the state for about four years now.
I want to just speak to that slightly.
The only reason that I have been offering
training is because currently what is out
there are these really long programs that
cost $10,
000 or such and there was a lot of people
just wanting some training around harm
reduction.
People are doing this work and have been
doing this work for a long time and I was
asked essentially by various people, hey,
can you just offer us some information
around safety and some basics?
Most of the trainings that I have been
doing have been attended by people that
are already doing this work and they were
just wanting to basically have community
because working alone and this is
probably not the safest option for people.
And it's interesting because lately there
has been people attending that are brand
new.
So I can see that there is a trend and
things are shifting.
And so today I'm going to talk a little
bit about the training model that I've
been, that I've developed.
I by no means have been telling people
that if you take my training,
then you can just, you're ready to,
you know,
start doing this work immediately.
That is not what I that's not been the
design of my training.
It's more about taking what I've learned
both from attending Theracill in Canada
as well as the work that I was doing
experientially and also following the
scientific research,
following the clinical models.
I want to make it also really clear that
I've not been doing any cultural
appropriation.
I don't,
I don't say that I'm working ceremonially.
I never have.
I'm working clinically.
And today what I plan to do is to review
a little bit about the training model.
I want to talk a little bit about the
treatment framework for client care.
I want to talk a little bit about some
proposed practicum options for the
straight, the state training program.
And then I'll obviously I'm here to
suggest equitable and safe implementation
in New Mexico.
So what I'm really wanting to do here is
just to provide some ideas for building a
safe,
ethical and culturally aware state
program.
And thank you very much, Brenda,
for inviting me to speak today.
So who am I and who do I think I am
having this presentation?
I am a licensed professional clinical
counselor in New Mexico, Colorado,
and Texas.
I was also licensed in Washington,
but I've let that lapse mostly because I
have been focusing most of my efforts
here in New Mexico.
I do have a private practice in Las
Cruces, NM, Mariposa Counseling Center,
and I have recently started a position of
Director of Education for Psychedelic
Assisted Therapy Association, Pata.
They originated in 2021 in Oregon.
Jason Burge is here today to support this
and maybe even answer some questions.
I've got a slide or two in here about his
model,
which I think is an important thing to
discuss in helping us to establish this
program.
And a big part of what Pata is trying to
do is to offer standardized education
across the nation so that as states
become a legalized,
they have a place to land to start
getting education and to start creating
community and networking.
I'm very excited to be a part of this.
Some of you know that I have been
Secretary for Decriminalized Psychedelics
New Mexico since last year.
I also offer not only psychedelic
assisted therapy as a facilitator,
but also as an educational from
educational aspect as well.
I'm trying to help people feel empowered
to do this work safely.
I've also had the benefit of being able
to write a book and release a documentary
around the the clinical version of this
work.
What I focus on primarily is ethical and
safe practices.
I think it's important that practitioners
are trained and that they are able to
receive supervision.
And I think it's really important that we
focus on client preparation and
integration frameworks,
specifically using the clinical model.
This is a medical model,
and I think it's important that, you know,
we're setting things up accordingly.
So I just want to quickly talk about what
I think the core pillars of psilocybin
facilitator training need to include.
There's definitely the knowledge, right?
We all need to understand the science,
the psychology, what are altered states,
what does all that mean?
And not only the science behind it,
the pharmacology,
the also just understanding how this
medicine works.
We also need clinical skills.
We need to know what preparation involves,
what is integration and how do we do that,
and also how do we facilitate in a way
that it makes the most sense following
again the clinical model.
Ethics are always important.
It tells us what our boundaries are,
how to keep people safe,
how to do this work responsibly.
And then I think experiential is also
just as important as the others.
Not only do I feel like everyone needs to
have a relationship with the medicine,
I also think that practicum is a great
way to help people feel confident and
learn how to do this work in a way that
isn't just, you know,
trial and error where people can have
backup and assistance in learning how to
do this work and just really quickly.
So if we follow all four of these pillars,
the focus and the hope is that we have
safe and effective facilitation.
So now before I go any further,
I do want to talk about this model that
Pata has put together that I think is
really important for us to discuss and to
become more aware of.
I think we tend as a group to just kind
of lump preparation and integration all
in as one.
But really there's there's areas in which
we have both therapeutic and we have
administrative preparation as well As for
integration.
So administration is obviously kind of
focusing on logistics, safety, compliance,
where therapeutic is more the
psychological,
emotional and clinical process.
In Oregon,
they're not allowed to actually use
therapy.
They're,
even though it's called a therapy program,
there's there's no allowance for
therapeutic techniques of any kind.
And so that's a big part of why prep and
integration have been separated there
where there is administrative preparation,
but there's no therapeutic preparation
unless somebody's going to a counselor or
to a therapist.
So if you go to Oregon,
you receive administration, sorry,
administrative prep,
you get the experience and you get that
integration from an administrative point
of view,
but you're not necessarily getting the
therapy piece that requires like another
level, you know,
and or them seeking additional care,
whether that be some people are are
working with their therapist and then
they're going to Oregon to get the
experience.
And then they have the pillows both
before and after where they're actually
getting the therapeutic experience here
in New Mexico.
It looks like I haven't really heard
anybody discuss this if they're going to
be separate.
It does sound I've heard a little bit
about offering like peer support guides,
etcetera,
to maybe help with the experience.
But I think it's important that we're
looking at this path here and
understanding that there's two different
kinds of prep and two different kinds of
integration.
In fact, using this model,
some people who don't want to have
anything to do with the experience can
still offer the prep and the integration,
while we have people on site that are
actually doing the administrative prep,
integration, and of course, facilitating.
So I think it's important that we're
examining this framework and
understanding what the differences are.
I've been attending the other
subcommittees and I know they're talking
already about how many sessions are going
to be required for preparation,
but I'm not really seeing the definitions
or the teasing out between therapeutic
preparation versus administrative
preparation,
being that we're doing a medical model
here in New Mexico.
Therapeutic prep and integration is
important.
And I from what I understand that is to
be included in this program,
but I do think it's really important that
we're understanding that, you know,
there's different levels at which people
can operate.
So if somebody doesn't want to become a
counselor,
they can still participate by being a
part of the experience and the
administrative prep and integration.
So I just wanted to like kind of point
that out.
I've also got a couple of slides here
that just distinguish what the difference
is between administrative preparation and
therapeutic preparation is.
So for administrative,
we're talking about documentation,
informed consent,
medical review and assessment, scheduling,
reviewing of policies, procedures,
expectations,
as well as setting up the environment and
having a safety plan.
Therapeutic preparation is more about
developing trust and the rapport in
setting your intentions,
exploring history, themes,
goals of this process, and then of course,
preparing for emotional and psychological
experiences.
A big part of this,
which I believe I'll talk about later, is,
you know,
how ready are they psychologically for
this experience?
They might be ready administratively,
like they might like, OK,
I made the time and I'm willing, you know,
I've got the schedule and I'm going to do
this.
But are they really ready for this
experience psychologically, emotionally?
These are things that I think as the,
you know,
maybe in the counselor point of view
where the practitioners will be utilizing
the therapeutic preparation to determine
these types of things.
And with respect to integration,
the administrative aspects include,
you know, again, scheduling documentation,
coordinating with other providers,
making sure that they have the
appropriate supports or their matrix is
sufficient and in place tracking outcomes.
I know that the research subcommittee is
doing a lot of work on collecting data
that would all be, you know,
under the administrative umbrella.
But then therapeutically,
it's more about processing insights.
What, what are the, you know,
what are some new patterns and new
perspectives that are coming up?
How do you actually apply those into
behavioral change,
making sure that they have continued
psychological support around their growth
and around the changes that are happening,
and then of course,
reinforcing self-awareness and these new
understandings.
So now I'm going to focus a little bit on
how I deliver my trainings.
I do a didactic instruction for the first
day,
and then on the second day there's an
experiential learning component.
And so for the didactic portion,
I am focusing on the science,
the pharmacology, the legal,
what are the regulations,
what are the contraindications and what
are the risks.
We talk about clinical skill development,
you know, how do you prepare clients?
How do you screen them?
What does non directive facilitation mean?
And then how to help people integrate.
The second day of my training is an
experiential where half the people choose
to dose and half will choose to guide.
And this will allow participants to have
their own experience in a Safeway.
Some people want to experience this
medicine,
and I think it's important that you do
experience the medicine prior to guiding
clients to fully understand this,
what this medicine is.
I mean, here's the thing, you know,
for a doctor,
you don't really have to have had cancer
to understand how chemo works and to
offer chemo to a client.
You can still do the same thing with
psilocybin.
But I will tell you that if you
understand this medicine personally,
it's going to make you much,
much better at the work you're doing with
and helping to guide the client.
And I think that having a place where
people can experience the medicine for
themselves is important.
And I do believe when I talk about
practicum later,
I think this is going to be an important
part of what we need to be offering
practitioners.
It's also on the second day,
I'm offering people a supervised
experience of guiding others.
What does that look like and feel like
and how?
And then they get to do it,
but knowing they have backup and knowing
they're not doing it by themselves.
Also being able to observe multiple
client sessions.
So when we, when I have my second day,
I might have like 3P3 practitioners are
dosing and then we may have four or five
guides.
So now we get to experience multiple
different experiences because No2
psilocybin journeys for anybody are the
same.
It's good to have, you know,
different examples to experience so that
it can build confidence and expertise.
And then of course,
I always offer an online integration
after the training.
So whoever dosed gets integration,
that's a key and important part of the
experience.
And I, you know,
usually they allow the other class
members to attend that integration so
that they can also get first hand
experience on what integration looks like.
So just a little bit more on the content
that I include.
I think it's important that we're talking
about the history and the cultural
context of this medicine.
The difference, you know,
between clinical and ceremonial use.
What the history has shown around the
suppression of research and how research
has emerged again,
and so grateful for that happening.
And then of course,
it's important to understand and be aware
of ethics around traditional medicine
origins.
Then of course,
moving on to the science and pharmacology,
I make sure people understand what you
know.
They know what psilocybin is,
how it interacts with the serotonin
receptors,
what is the default mode network,
what is ego dissolution and how that
impacts the experience.
Although I focus on dosing ranges and the
pharmakinetics around that,
I also talk about the legal and
regulatory landscape,
that it is a federal,
federally scheduled one drug that a lot
of states are trying to decriminalize or
implement these types of regulated
programs and what the responsibilities
are within the medical frameworks.
I also make sure to take time to talk
about risk awareness and participant
screening.
Not everybody is going to be well suited
for this experience.
We want to make sure that there's
psychological stability,
that they're ready for this experience,
and that they don't have any physical
health exclusions.
I think that the participant subcommittee
is doing a great job of establishing what
those exclusions are.
And so I've been able to be a part of
that and see the amazing work that's
happening and all these subcommittees.
It's also important to assess the
medication that they're taking.
There are there are medications that will
interfere or dampen the experience,
antidepressants, antipsychotics,
anti anxiety medications, benzos, opiates.
You know,
it's interesting because I'm starting to
see a lot of stuff around semi glutides
that's coming up.
I was able to identify four years ago
that semi glutides significantly
interfere with the experience.
And you know,
these are all important things to
consider and some of these things will
literally rule somebody out if they're
taking certain things.
It's just not safe for them to be doing
this type of treatment and then of course,
always having a medical consultation
whenever appropriate.
Somebody has a severe cardiovascular or
if they have diabetes,
I want to make sure that, you know,
they get medical clearance.
Are they, is their diabetes being managed?
Is it not?
If they have severe cardiovascular,
chances are they're probably not going to
get a doctor to give a clearance.
It depends.
I'm not a doctor, I don't claim to be.
So I think it is important that we're
utilizing that, that Ave.
when appropriate and necessary.
I also utilize www.psychedelicinteraction.
com.
Kristen Speer,
she is a pharmacist up in Denver who
created this website that allows you to
type in whatever medications you're
taking.
Then it will give you any
contraindications.
It'll basically give you information
about those medications.
Because I'm not a doctor,
I'm not the one going to tell anybody
what you know,
anything about their medicine.
So I will refer to this website which
will give a print out and then they can
then schedule a consult with that
pharmacist For more information because
that's not, again,
knowing what my scope of practice is.
That is not I'm not a doctor.
All right,
further risk awareness and and
participant screening,
we're also looking for certain conditions
that are contraindicated.
I already mentioned some of them.
And then of course, managing any risk,
making sure that participants are aware
of what challenging experiences might
happen,
setting realistic expectations and in
making sure that they have appropriate
support systems in their matrix.
When they leave, are they,
are they going back to,
to a domestic violence situation?
Well,
that's not going to be a good a good
appropriate treatment for them if they're
not going to be safe when they get home.
Examining these things are really,
really important.
So we also spend quite a bit of time
talking about the stages of psilocybin
assisted therapy, how preparation the,
the session itself and then the
integration, how they're all important.
And then of course with making sure that
you know, you're,
you're building the rapport with them
during preparation, you do the,
the assessment, you create intentions,
you manage expectations,
establishing set setting and matrix.
These are all important things.
During the session,
we want to make sure that we're offering
a non directive facilitation.
Planting seeds is not OK.
It's not our job to tell clients what
they're experiencing.
Providing a supportive presence and being
able to monitor the experience is what's
important.
And then also providing that containment,
A psychological and emotional containment.
Of course, integration.
We know that integration is critical.
Processing the insights and the emotions
are really important,
translating those experiences into
meaningful change and then getting the
continued support necessary.
You know,
doing the medicine by itself might
provide therapeutic outcomes, it might.
But preparation and integration are
what's going to align everything towards
the positive outcomes.
So one of the things that I forgot to
mention on the Pata slide that talked
about the process, you know, the,
the experience itself is not psilocybin
assisted therapy.
That's, that's just, you know,
having a journey.
Psilocybin assisted therapy includes
preparation and integration.
It's a process.
It's a process that's going to take a
minimum of if it's,
if it's being done with proper time in
between a minimum of four weeks,
but it could be like 8 weeks depending on
how long it takes for you to prepare and
how an integration by the way,
can happen for months,
maybe even years sometimes.
So it's a minimum,
I would say a minimum of three to four
weeks,
but it could this process could be years
long.
It's not going to be this really fast
quick thing.
It, it, it,
we need to be taking time for the
preparation and, and the integration.
OK.
So moving forward to the facilitation
model,
I'm very much again follow the clinical,
the clinical model,
which is to support participants on their
inner process,
not direct their experience.
So things that include that are important
to include as core principles.
We want to encourage curiosity,
accept all the emotions that come up,
maintain calm and being attentive,
avoiding interpretation or providing any
advice.
And then of course,
we want to support that they have
autonomy and making meaning of their
experience from what they as as they see
it, not as we see it.
As facilitators.
Also,
a big part of what I believe in in the
work that I do is creating intentions for
a journey.
I would say that this has been the single
most important piece of preparation and
integration.
And the experience itself is to help
participants define their intentions by
creating intentions that they identify
during the preparation process.
It allows almost for the healing to start.
It's almost like they're beginning to
think about and process what is it that
I'm wanting from this experience.
And if we're doing it well,
we don't even need the list by the time
you get to the experience because they
already know they're already locked and
loaded.
What the things are that they want to
work on.
You know, do you have to have intentions?
No, but for therapeutic outcomes,
I would say that this is the most
important piece is in preparation and in
integration is to have been reflecting on
the areas that you want to heal from.
And when you get in,
when the medicine takes hold,
these things are already present.
And we know that psilocybin is an
amplifier and it will literally just
amplify what you've been thinking about
and focusing on for the weeks prior.
I also will feed participants what is on
their list.
If, for example,
if they are having a hard time with
something,
let's just say they're going through a
loop where they're experiencing something
over and over and over again.
And when that happens,
usually after the third time,
it's not valuable anymore.
It's just like a repetitive experience.
I usually tell clients that when that
happens, let me know.
We will, you know,
we'll probably have you switch positions,
switch the song, go to the restroom,
do something and then I will feed them
one of their intentions that they,
you know,
that they prepared and that will then
take them in,
back in in a different direction.
I have found that using these intentions
is also been the best way to assess the
experience in the integration phase.
In the beginning of doing this work,
a lot of people would come to me and say,
well,
my intention is to be open to the
medicine.
And I thought, wow, that's great.
But what I've learned is, yeah,
I think everyone needs to have that
intention.
Like that should already be an attention.
If it's not an intention,
then they're not ready for this
experience.
That's part of being ready.
I have found that when people just have
that as their intention,
they come through it going, yeah, OK,
I got some stuff.
But they're not able to actually see the
profound implications of the experience
as well as if they had a list of
intentions that we can now go through
with them and they can see the shifts for
themselves.
And I'm going to tell you that nine times
out of 10,
people come through and 90% of their list
has been addressed or no longer is a
thing.
I find that intentions are critical.
So intentions provide direction without
imposing control on the experience
because they created those intentions.
I may have helped them formulate them,
but they are their intentions and we're
using the words that they provide.
I don't change the wording.
I literally read it exactly as is to help
them focus on their experience.
Without intentions,
they may have an amazing experience,
very much like an Alice in Wonderland
going down a rabbit hole.
With intentions,
I'm I know they're going to work on the
things they want to work on and the
therapeutic outcomes will be dramatically
improved as a result.
It's also important to teach people how
to manage challenging experiences.
You know when it's not uncommon for
people to be experiencing anxiety, fear,
or panic,
especially during the induction phase.
It can also be that they're having to
relive something in order to work through
it.
Emotional release and trauma activation
are are are definitely possible.
People can be confused and disoriented as
well.
So it's important that facilitators know
like when to to have them lean in to what
they're experiencing versus when are we
going to try to, you know,
help them kind of come out and then go
back in in a different direction.
It's also really important as
facilitators that we maintain a calm,
grounded presence.
I've seen it over and over again where
practitioners get very uncomfortable when
somebody starts to emote and it's,
or even if they're getting angry and
they're starting to release, you know,
maybe they're, they're starting to scream.
It's important to help people feel
comfortable that this is part of their
process that they need to go through and
providing reassurance and orientation to
the client to help them focus on the
things that they want to focus on
supporting the participant and staying
with the experience so that they can get
the therapeutic outcomes.
You know, growth requires.
It requires us to sometimes go through
challenge and these experiences are not
always very pleasant.
Sometimes they are hard.
But the outcomes,
if you stick with it and you,
you're providing the safety and the space
they need in the container,
they can get through it with very,
very positive outcomes having actually
worked through that trauma or that fear.
And then of course,
we always want to adjust the environment
when needed.
It's,
it's not unusual for somebody to say
something about the environment that's
bothering them, the temperature,
the lighting.
And it's important as facilitators that
we're helping to address that.
One of the things I do want to say about
the way in which I operate,
the the way in which I facilitate,
is I tell people that I want them to let
me take care of them,
lean into the experience and allow me to
do all the things.
If they don't like the song on their
playlist, let me change it for them.
If they need more water,
I will go get it for them.
I have had many,
many people after their journeys come to
me and say that the most therapeutic part
of their experience was the fact that
they didn't have to worry about anything
and that there was somebody there caring
for them and taking care of every need
they had.
If they need to use the restroom,
I'm going to walk them there.
I'm not going to just say, oh,
just give them like direct them to the
restroom.
No,
I'm literally going to have them put
their hands on the my shoulders and I'm
walking them to the restroom.
Many clients have said that having
somebody take care of them teaches them
to take care of themselves,
especially when they're the,
they're under the neuroplasticity of the
medicine and they're allowing somebody to
take care of them.
Chances are when they leave,
they're going to allow others in a little
bit more in helping to take care of
themselves and hopefully they're going to
prioritize taking care of themselves as
well.
Integration is,
is extremely important and it is a,
it's interesting because a lot of people
come to me and they say, well,
what exactly is integration?
And integration is essentially
counselling.
You know,
when we have a client that has an insight,
we're helping them to apply that into
their life.
That's what we do as counsellors.
Usually they come to counselling because
they're recognizing something big in
their life.
For example,
I'm realizing that my husband isn't good
for me and I need to examine this
relationship and see if this is the right
thing for me.
Well,
a counselor is there to have allow them
the safety to explore what they need to
explore to be able to apply these new
insights that they're having.
We're doing the same exact thing with
integration,
except the insights happened during the
experience, right?
They're these big insights where when ego
goes offline,
we're making connections that we don't
normally make.
And so it's the role of the facilitator
when it comes to integration is to help
them to like just to help them reflect on
what's coming up for them without
imposing our own meaning,
but allowing them to make meaning out of
what they experienced themselves.
We're helping to support their emotional
processing,
translating insights into action.
How do I apply this?
Now that I understand this new thing
about my mother,
how do I how do I deal with her?
How do I work with her?
So what are some integration practices,
structured reflection and discussion,
identifying patterns and new perspectives
and supporting behavioral change.
And then there's ongoing support.
You know, insights can unfold,
unfold over time.
I've known people that can have insights
a year after their their journey.
It's because maybe there was a piece of
it that, you know,
not necessarily that they forgot,
but they just didn't focus on.
But then a year later something happens
and Oh my gosh, I understand it now.
So I think follow up sessions can
reinforce outcomes and having continued
support improves safety and effectiveness.
I've worked with a client before for a
couple months and then I'll I'll hear
from them like 3 months later because oh,
I have to process a new part of my
experience.
So I think it's important that as
facilitators were providing that safety
in that space, that ongoing relationship,
even if it's a few months later,
because there might be something new that
comes up that's related to their journey
that still needs to be processed.
So as I say here,
participants often process insights for
weeks after the session,
which is why integration is so essential.
I had many people say to me after a
journey, Oh my gosh,
I've had all these amazing insights and
now I have to go home and just apply
these to where nothing else is changed or
different.
How do I take this new meaning and
understanding that I have and apply it in
a world where no one else gets it?
That can actually 'cause people harm if
they're not integrating.
So integration is key and critical.
So now I wanted to switch gears and talk
a little bit about practicum.
I'm super excited about being able to
offer practicum.
This is new.
This is something that doesn't really
exist out there.
I mean,
I know some of these programs offer a
little bit of practicum, like maybe a,
a journey or two.
What I want to be able to do is I want to
be able to offer like a week long
training of practicum if people want it,
so they can get multiple experiences with
multiple people,
not just like one person that I guided.
I think that it's going to be remarkable
for New Mexico to have practicums and I
hope all other states end up following
suit.
So the purpose of practicum is to help
bridge the knowledge and the clinical
application.
So to be able to to to use it in a real
time setting to develop competency and to
ensure safe and ethical facilitation.
So as I've already mentioned before,
it's important that people have like a
supervised facilitation experience,
that they be allowed to have a journey on
their own to experience it,
that they'd be able to observe other
sessions, other clients,
and then be able to have structured
feedback and integration of their
learning.
So I'm would like to offer two options
for practicum.
One of them, which might be one thing,
I saw Brenda,
you said 6 to 8 hours for practicum.
That's really only one experience.
I would actually recommend more than that.
I would recommend at least two
experiences.
I guess it depends on what we're talking
about.
Are we talking about people that have
already been doing this for a while or
are we talking about people that are
brand new to this?
If they're brand new to this,
then I think they're going to need like a
week long practicum.
That's just my opinion.
But I do think this option here,
option 1 is where you got you dose and
you guide.
So on one day you would dose and other
facilitators would guide you,
and then on another day it's switched so
that you then get to experience what it's
like to guide.
This will give people, you know,
the structure they need to both
participate, observe,
and then practice facilitation.
This will help people engage in their own
healing work,
develop a relationship with the medicine,
understand the internal experience,
and then also build confidence in
facilitation.
So I see this being like a 2 day
experience, maybe not even back-to-back.
Maybe it's like one weekend,
one person doses and then maybe the next
weekend, you know, it gets switched.
That's really reasonable.
Thank you.
I just wanted to chime in there just just
to make sure that I, you know,
I'm not being, you know,
I am paying attention here.
But yeah, I think, yeah,
from start to finish, yeah, more,
more hours for people need that.
So yeah, I absolutely do.
Yeah.
Great.
Thanks.
So the second option is the immersive
experience that I was talking about.
It's a multiple day practical and it's
focused on real clients.
So what I would really like to do when
I'm when Ioffer this is I want to be able
to have clients receive this experience
at low or no cost.
And then we actually so because they know
they're going to be in a practicum
experience where people are learning.
So there is more flexibility and,
and you know,
this way we can actually offer treatment
to people here in New Mexico.
Like I said it either low or no cost
where we have facilitators come.
And what I would what ideally the way I
see it is it would be like maybe a week
long where before the practicum begins,
you are assigned to clients that you're
going to help prepare probably online.
Unless we can do it in person,
just depending logistically how that
would work.
But then you would come and you would
guide either like Monday,
Wednesday or Tuesday, Thursday.
And then other facilitators are also
guiding.
So you end up with 10 to 16 client
journeys that you've experienced over the
four days.
You're responsible for two of them
primarily,
but you have backup and you're being
supported through the entire experience
and you get to essentially facilitate
with a cohort where everybody is,
like I said, responsible for two clients.
So by the end, if we've got eight people,
then we've got 16 clients.
This gives people a wide range of
experiences and exposure that that's
going to help build confidence,
that's going to help build expertise.
And then maybe the last day Friday is
like, you know,
an integration day or maybe it's too much
to do in one week.
Maybe we split it up over 2 weeks.
Maybe we come for a couple days,
a couple days.
I don't know yet exactly what that's
going to look like.
But I do think that this is going to be
the fastest and best way for us to get
people feeling competent,
especially since we've got to get things
moving fast in this state.
So this is something that I think that we
should require for people that have no
experience guiding so that they can feel
by the end of this immersive experience,
they are feeling much more comfortable
and confident doing this work.
So now switching gears a little bit to
what are some of the things that I think
we need to be considering with respect to
this program.
I do think we need to have access
pathways for individuals without licenses
without, you know, degrees.
I saw on the list that doesn't look like
that's in there.
So I don't know if that's something that
will be added,
but I think that if somebody has to go
through an extensive training program,
they they can at a minimum do the
facilitation, right, the admin,
the experience and then the the
administrative.
And then maybe we have the counselor
doing the psychological pieces on the
other ends.
I also think we want to make sure that
we're including Pueblos, tribes, nations,
and my idea around this,
which I know it's just my idea and I
don't know if anybody really cares what
my idea is,
but I have this platform so I'm going to
go ahead and share it.
I actually think we should provide a
number of facilitator slots based on
population for these communities.
So if you know,
they and then they'll have the elders
decide who gets those positions because
they're not going to have education and
licenses and degrees.
They've been doing this their whole life
in a very different way.
And they,
that doesn't make them any less suited
for this work.
And I think that if we just like did a
per capita thing,
like if you have this much population,
you get this number of positions that the
elders will assign.
But then in order to maintain their
licensure,
they have to maintain CES just like the
rest of us, right?
They would still have to attend ethics
trainings and all the other things that
we're all going to have to do on a
routine basis.
And then I,
I like seeing that this is already kind
of,
you're already talking about this is
recognizing people that do have prior
experience grandfathering individuals
that have training and certifications.
Of course,
we need to have New Mexico specific
trainings and jurisprudence around the
laws of New Mexico.
I do think it's important that we are
including ethics and professional
responsibility.
I want to make sure that people
understand what their scope of practice
is.
Like, for example, I'm not a doctor,
I don't claim to be a doctor,
and I don't really want to be doing
things that are perceived as though I
think I know you know what a,
what a doctor would would say or do.
I think it's important that we're all
keeping clear on what our boundaries are
and our scopes of practice,
wanting to make sure that we're
protecting participants.
They're in vulnerable states.
I had heard about somebody who during a
journey they were telling people, oh,
we'll work on that later,
which was their way of getting additional
business.
And I think that's completely wrong.
We shouldn't be planting any seeds during
a journey.
We don't want to make people dependent on
us.
Just because I planted a seed during
their journey,
telling them that they're going to need
me later, that's not OK.
It's important that we focus on harm
reduction and safety screening,
risk awareness,
helping people prepare and supporting
them properly through the process,
making sure there's ongoing integration
and follow up care.
So even though there are integration
sessions,
individual sessions that are being
offered afterwards,
I hope that the state program will offer
maybe integration,
like online integration,
like maybe weekly where anybody who has
attended or received this treatment can
attend Integrations may be at low or no
cost, may be covered by insurance,
having an ongoing integration system
where people can get what they need,
even if it's months after their treatment.
Obviously,
I'm a big proponent of experiential
training.
That's why I think that practicum is
going to be so important.
I also am a big believer that everyone
needs to understand what this medicine is.
So I think understanding altered states
does improve safety and effectiveness.
So on closing again,
just thank you so much for allowing me to
speak.
I just think that well trained
facilitators are the primary safeguard in
any psilocybin program.
Thank you very much.
Thank you Catherine.
That was that was a superb presentation.
Thank you so much for that.
So now we're going to go back to there
were a lot of questions in the chat.
Some of them were answered by Dominic
already.
So I'm going to kind of popcorn this a
little bit.
Does anyone have any questions for the
Department of Health here or Catherine or
myself or Dominic?
If you wanted to raise your hand,
we'll get to,
we'll do a raised hand 1st and then we'll
do a chat and we'll go back and forth
like that.
All right,
And I see Lita Fatimi's hand up.
Doctor Fatimi, I have enabled your mic.
Thank you so much, Catherine.
That was fantastic.
Thank you so much for just awesome,
awesome presentation.
One of the things that we have just never
really discussed or touched on is the
recommendation regarding the frequency of
which a person is recommended to do the
medicine journey.
You know, in our work, what we talk about,
it is not more than every three to six
months so that you have time for maybe,
you know, even less frequent than that.
But that has come up in the past.
And I think it's an important point to
touch on.
I also have had, you know,
people who will do a sell cyber and
journey for the first time.
They're like, Oh my God,
this is so amazing to feel like, you know,
more complete.
And then they think that doing more
psychedelics gives them more healing,
and then they'll go to retreat center in
South America.
And then.
And they've really been tapped into
escapism after that and into psychosis
and on and on and on.
And so I think it is very important as
educators to talk about that,
the frequency of the journey itself,
especially with Mac reducing.
Thank you so much for all the work you've
put into this.
Appreciate you all.
Thank you, Doctor Fatemi.
Yeah, I,
I think there's a lot that that we still
need to discuss about what happens,
you know, during and after journey.
And I think preparation for the client,
if you're really educating your client
First off about it,
about the these journeys that, yes,
you know,
how are people going to pursue that
afterwards that if you do educate your
clients well that you're doing, you know,
you're doing the best job you can.
And you know,
if people choose to do that afterwards,
you know, that's kind of a Gray area,
But you know,
caution with safety around this and
assessments and doing the due diligence
as a,
as a therapist or a medical provider.
I think that's where we need to really
hone in on the education piece when we're
talking with our clients.
Next,
I want to kind of jump into the chat here.
The first one we have up here is Luita
Krikorian.
And she was asking what is the timeline
for various educational programs to begin
applying for approval.
And this has not yet been determined.
It is part of what we these meetings are
working through the requirements and
application process at the current pace
of progress.
Late summer,
early fall is most likely before
applications are opened and the
regulations have to be promulgated.
OK, next.
Does anybody have a hand raised for
another question here?
And again,
as a reminder to the but to raise your
hand,
there's an icon at the top with a hand
that says raise,
might be on the left or right depending
on different people's systems,
but should just have a hand that says
raise.
OK.
I'll go to the next in the chat,
It's from Kate Hawk.
I appreciate this is moving quickly and
have concerns about needing more training
especially for ethics and safety.
Colorado had a 25 hour program for
experienced practitioners that gave time
for discussion as well as information.
I found it valuable even after extensive
practice and teaching etcetera.
That's valuable.
Yes, of course, you know,
as far as the ethics is concerned,
as I said in the beginning of the meeting
today when I was reading the the document
for us clinicians,
we usually have a 12 hour ethics that we
need to meet.
So I think having the, you know,
the ethics part of that in this program
would qualify for some or all we could do
the 12 hour requirement for the licensure
and, and we, we as clinicians,
we have to do 40 hours of Ceus within a
A2A2 year time frame to keep up our
licensure.
So I just want to kind of reiterate that
a little bit.
Let's see anyone else have their hand
raised.
It's looks like next we've got Chris
Pisguski and Chris, I have larger mic.
You can talk when ready.
Hi, Brenda.
Hi, everyone.
Good to talk to you all.
So it sounds like that this committee is
committed to offering reciprocity to
people who have trained in Colorado and
Oregon.
So is that going to be maybe a baseline
for our training here in New Mexico as
far as ours?
And you know there is about a 25 hour
difference between the two programs.
So would,
would Oregon have to make those hours up
or would we have a baseline starting with
organs kind of hours and curriculum?
The good question, Chris,
thank you for that.
I the way I see it and is that they have
already been incorporated in our system
and being a resident as well because I,
I don't know what,
how long you have to be a resident.
I think it's six months in New Mexico and
that's just the way our licenses are,
are set up.
In order to practice here in New Mexico,
you have to be a resident and however,
if you've been trained in another state
or country for that matter,
you would and you're certified and or
licensed in another state or country.
If you come here and you're a resident
here in New Mexico and you want to be
licensed,
you just need to go through the short
program for people that have already been
been trained in, you know,
psilocybin or psychedelics.
So that in in my mind that's how it would
work.
Well,
let's say hypothetically we say everyone
that is licensed and has gone through a
program somewhere else here in New Mexico,
you would have to take the 15 hours of
that extra training for to practice here
in New Mexico.
So that's, that's hypothetically speaking,
that's what we're we're kind of looking
at in order.
It's so you're not spending thousands and
thousands of dollars on getting trained
and, you know,
all those hours that you've already put
into it.
You know, here in New Mexico,
we want to meet the this kind of fast
track into practicing here now from start
to finish.
We we really haven't come to a conclusion
from that people.
Let's say you,
you want to get taught here in New Mexico
as far as Colorado and Oregon go,
if you get trained here in New Mexico,
I have no idea if you could take what
you've learned here in New Mexico and go
to Colorado or Oregon and have that
transfer because this is there.
They came first,
but we're trying to design something here
that's for New Mexico and New Mexico
people that are practicing here as
clinicians.
So I hope that answered your question.
I think in a roundabout way,
I guess what I'm saying is it sounds like
we want to offer reciprocity for people
who have been trained as a facilitator in
Oregon and Colorado.
Is that correct?
Yes,
we want to be able to accept people from
other states or other countries that are
that want to practice here.
So that's that's why we're looking at
more of bringing in that reciprocity
piece in and that they would only have to
take a an additional learning process in
other words,
in order to practice here in New Mexico.
Do you mind if I keep going on this
thread or do we?
Yeah, no, go ahead, go ahead, keep going.
OK, So if we,
if we are going to offer reciprocity,
then it kind of stands to reason that we
have a similar model,
training model as either Oregon or
Colorado,
but but they do vary slightly and one of
them takes pretty significant more time
to to get.
And so I'm curious if if we've kind of if
you all picked one that we're going to
model it after or if there's thought to
how that's going to work.
OK, Dominic,
I I think could answer that a lot better
than I.
Thank you, Brenda and and thank you,
Chris.
It's a good question.
And just to kind of clarify,
one thing to remember is different
licensures do have different requirements.
So that's a part of why anybody who has a
particular licensure will still have to
follow their requirements with regard to
that licensure.
As to the the reciprocity,
as was discussed in a much earlier
meeting,
what we're really looking at is we want
to ensure people are still trained in New
Mexico.
And that's where the idea that that
Brenda had presented showing that,
showing that anybody who has been trained
in those other states would then be able
to take sort of a, a refresher course,
I think is how Brenda said it.
But essentially doing some modules that
are specific to New Mexico to ensure that
they actually any gaps that might be
there are covered.
As to new programs that's still being
developed and how exactly that will work,
we're not quite sure yet,
but it's been noted in the chat, You know,
Doctor Fatemi put in a comment about
competency and that's a part of what
we've talked about.
And like Ellen has about how the
competencies will be evaluated,
we do have to determine that at this
point.
And one of the things we've also talked
about is if you go through the programs
in either Colorado or in Oregon,
you have to go through the entire program.
So you have to meet all of those hours
that may not actually necessarily be
appropriate depending on the experience
or the licensure of the different
individuals going through here.
So we're also looking at what would we
want to do to ensure that we actually
have a really good educational program
for those clinicians and facilitators.
So we haven't actually determined that
and the reciprocity in the beginning is
really a starting point to get the
program going.
There most likely will be an end point on
that where we would no longer accept
somebody who has been trained elsewhere
that they would have to go through a
program certified by New Mexico to be
able to be to do this.
But we would still grandfather those
people who had already been in there.
So this is really that starting point to
ensure that we have practitioners and
facilitators, you know within it.
But the point you bring up about the
discrepancy between the Colorado
requirements and the Oregon requirements
is a good one.
And that is actually true with a lot of
different licensures in different states
where they will have vastly different
requirements for maintaining or even
obtaining that licensure.
What we really need to decide so is while
we look at those programs and see what is
appropriate, what's going to be good.
And we've been talking with a lot of
different people who actually are
facilitating lots of those programs and
people who are doing that here,
including quite a few people who are on
this meeting,
so that we can figure out what is
actually going to be the best program
educationally.
And not just going, you know, with saying,
oh, well, Colorado has done this,
we're just going to adopt it.
Oregon has done this,
we're just going to adopt it.
We want to ensure that it's a good
program.
That may not be the point for the very
beginning,
but what we develop over time and in the
very beginning allowing for that
reciprocity.
Because we have many people who are here
in New Mexico who have gotten that
training and will be excellent
facilitators and clinicians.
And so we don't want to cause them
additional burden by saying go and take
it another course that's going to cost
you 8 or 10,
000 or however much it cost to go through
it.
We want you to be able to practice that.
You've already learned.
So those are some good questions.
And as we dive into the details in this
committee about the different areas and
sections and competencies,
that's some of what we have to determine.
But in the initial stage, yes,
that reciprocity will be there.
It may be time limited and that time
frame hasn't been determined yet.
And some of it will depend on how much,
you know what the demand here is in New
Mexico.
So just wanted to to I, I hope that helps.
There's still a lot to be done in this
area especially and I probably just made
it even more confusing.
OK, I see a thumbs up from Chris.
I'll take the visit.
OK, thank you, Dominic,
Thank you so much for the explanation.
Yeah, sometimes I'm not that, you know, I,
I don't have that ready on the tongue
here to explain.
I just wanted to,
to go through some of the, the,
the chats and then we'll go through a
couple of chats and then I'll we'll
answer some more raised hands here.
So Maya says,
is there any place for role for people in
New Mexico model for those who do not
hold a clinical medical license?
And then Vincent, I echo this question.
I am finishing up training in Colorado
and there is a clinical and non clinical
licensure pathways.
Will that be offered in New Mexico for
those who do not have a medical or mental
health degree?
And then Gregory said that part.
Thank you for voicing that experiential
knowledge for providers.
So basically we really are not looking at
right now as like a Co facilitator
pathway yet.
That's for further discussion.
But we've got to remember that this is
the medical psilocybin program here and
that if you do not have a medical degree
or or a mental health degree,
but you have an alternative type of
certification,
we'll have to look at that a little bit
more closely.
But for right now,
as far as initiating the roll out here is
that the people that will be practicing
will be people that are are licensed in
mental health or medical as far as I know.
OK, next raised hand.
All right, we've got Jen Clemente and Jen,
I've enabled your mic and unmute whenever
you're ready.
Yeah, there you go.
OK, thanks so much.
So, yeah, so in my mind,
I'm trying to think about like the design
of the application to become a
facilitator.
And I'm thinking about all the the sort
of fields and variables you're going to
have to look at.
So it'll be interesting when you get gets
when it gets to that time.
And maybe that could be another session
just to look at how do you apply and sort
of what do you know,
how do you fill out that application and
if it's open-ended, close it,
if it's closed or opened and whatnot.
But my question really comes to spiritual
dimensions of of training and care.
Catherine, in your excellent presentation,
which was really inclusive and really
considered so many things,
I did notice that the word spirituality
and spiritual was missing.
And I don't know if that was by design or
if that was something that you know that
you're thinking like, OK,
so the chaplain or spiritual care
provider who may be as part of that care
team,
would that would be their area of
specialization?
But I really do think,
and in the presentation I gave,
I guess a month ago,
I touched on this topic a little bit
about how I thought it was important,
at least for anybody on the care team to
have some awareness of spiritual
dimensions of care.
And you know,
sort of that depth psychology angle as
well.
Anything that goes into transpersonal or
having an understanding of the spiritual
experience and spiritual emergency that
can come through as well,
spiritual emergence and emergency.
So I'm wondering if you would be so kind
as to touch on that and your your
thoughts on kind of how spirituality fits
in, in training.
Well, yeah,
thank you for pointing that out.
It was actually by design just because
again,
trying to kind of stay in my scope of
practice.
Generally speaking, however,
I will say you cannot remove spirituality
from this experience.
Like that's just not an option, right?
It is a spiritual experience and that
that we do need training around that.
I believe the CIS guidelines for
practitioners states in there that we
need to have spiritual intelligence,
which I actually should think should be
more like spiritual competence,
not so much intelligence,
because I don't think you need to know
every possible spirituality to do this
work.
But I agree with you that there does need
to be some education around spirituality
and how that comes into play.
And I think this is something we need to
definitely have more conversations around.
Great, Thank you so much.
And I,
I look forward to having them with you.
And I just wanted to remind everyone that
in the document that I wrote up in our
first meeting,
that does include pastors and spiritual
healers in in this as well.
So just to make a point of that.
And of course,
if you are having a spiritual experience
that, you know,
therapists also need that training,
that will be also included in the
training as well and what to expect.
I mean, I also think though,
just to say real, real quickly,
I think that as counselors,
that's what we're trained to do, right?
We're trained to honor a client's
experience,
regardless of whether it's spiritual,
emotional, mental.
It's almost like that's,
that's part of what we do.
When somebody shows up and they're
telling us about, you know,
their perception of what they're
experiencing,
it's not our place ever to tell them no,
that's not right.
Or, you know,
our job is to hold a container for them
to explore whatever it is that they're
experiencing.
And I feel like spirituality is no
different.
So I feel like we're already sort of
trained to accept whatever anybody brings
to the experience.
And especially in a psychedelic
experience where there's so much
creativity, right?
There's creatures on trains showing up
asking if somebody wants cake.
Like,
there's things happening that aren't
logical, that don't make sense.
And it's all about allowing for the
person to have that full experience,
whether it's mental,
emotional or spiritual.
So I mean,
I think that that as far as like us,
our responsibility as a facilitator is to
allow whatever they're experiencing to be
their experience.
Well, thank you both for for that.
It's,
it's really important to have these
discussions.
OK.
Going back to the chat,
I'm going to kind of skip over some of
them because some of them have already
been answered with Chris's question about
certification in other states from Kate
Hawk.
And Dominic posted the New Mexico
resource for clinicians and statute for
licensing because Maya had a question
about that.
So I'm going to skip down here.
OK, so Eileen Brewer had some concerns.
She says I have serious concerns about
requiring this model.
1 of the beautiful things about New
Mexico's law is that it's meant to be
expansive.
We are starting with treating just four
areas, PTSD, depression, Sud,
and end of life care.
But the 5th bullet point was other
conditions as approved.
This board has decided to go with just
four areas to start approximately
appropriately since more could be
overwhelming.
However,
very quickly New Mexico does intend to
expand and 1st area that makes sense in
chronic pain treatment.
There is a vast amount of evidence for
psychedelics as treatments for chronic
pain and a desperate need since there is
very little safe effective treatment for
chronic pain.
However,
the treatment protocols being developed
for psychedelics for chronic pain are
mostly very much medical,
with the medicine used like you would
like you would any other medicine,
and very much more frequently than you
would use it for depression or PTSD.
Creating requirements for this program
that will be difficult to change later
will further distance this desperate
population from accessing treatment that
may save their lives.
Requirements like mental and
administration preparation and
integration before and after every single
administration session will make this
treatment and accessible for someone who
needs to take 1 to 2 grams every five
days,
or for someone who wants to micro dose,
or for someone who may need to titrate up
OR.
Oregon has already encountered this
challenge and needed to reconsider the
burdensome requirements.
In addition,
end of life care already includes pain
care.
If we tell someone seeking end of life
care that they need to go through this
lengthy and burdensome process,
it may create barrier to excess for
people who don't need it all and just
want relief from pain and a broader view
on death.
While these are strongly recommended for
people treating difficult health
conditions,
I don't know if this is a good idea to
codify it as requirement for every single
patient in every single circumstance.
In addition,
if providers are not aware of the
developing protocols for pain treatment,
those who have read in the media that
psychedelics help treat pain may seek
apat model experience,
get an appropriate treatment for their
needs,
and then wind up more hopeless than
treatment fails.
Pain is only one reason.
Consider this.
There are likely dozens I don't know
about.
Some very, very, very good points here,
Eileen.
Yes, as a clinician,
I would say that the majority of the
clients that I have right now have
chronic pain and this I,
I think we will be looking at this as
well.
I don't know what you have to say about
that, Dominic, but it,
it's one thing that I guess we need to
look at.
So who else has their hand raised?
Who's next?
Next, we've got Shane McDaniel.
And Shane, I have enabled her mic.
Can you hear me?
Yep.
Yeah, that means it's working all right.
So I hate to just keep hashing out this
reciprocity issue,
but as a currently certified integration
coach that went through one of the
expensive programs already would and,
and talking about grandfathering in
people with Colorado or Oregon
certifications,
my certification isn't out of Oregon or
Colorado.
It's I mean, I treat,
I can treat people all over the United
States,
all over the world already as long as
they, you know, want to hire me.
My certification program didn't have
anything to do with the Oregon
requirements or the Colorado requirements.
So is that that would be a separate
reciprocity issue than somebody who just
had met the say the Colorado requirements
or the Oregon requirements or am I wrong?
As I see it,
what we were talking about earlier is
grandfathering people in that have
already been through a certification
process or licensing process that
included their education and
grandfathering in.
What we're looking at right now is adding
the new our,
our New Mexico reciprocity program,
which will only,
it will be very short requirement hours.
So I, I understand it sounds like you're,
you're able to do this in, in, in,
in many places.
But here in New Mexico we would require,
like for instance,
we would require you to do,
I don't know what it would be right now.
I'm looking at 10 hours, but it'll,
let's say it'll be like 25 hours for you
to, to practice here in New Mexico.
Is that correct, Dominic?
So,
so I mean we haven't determined exactly
what that module will look like.
So I mean that's a part of some of the
continued discussions.
But I do need to be clear,
it has to be an approved program.
So it has to be a program that's already
been approved and we can utilize other
states because they are regulatory
agencies as that we can say they have
done some of that due diligence.
So it it has to be a program that has
already been approved by one of those
other states that has this.
So if it's just a program that's out
there because they offer psilocybin
training,
but has not been approved by a Regulatory
agency,
that's not going to be something we're
going to be able to accept.
As far as that Vincent,
the programs in both Colorado and Oregon
do list down what programs,
what educational programs they have
already approved.
And, and,
and part of the reason behind this is
because there have been educational
programs that have actually been that
have been problematic.
And so it has to have gone through an
approval process.
And here in the beginning of the program,
quite frankly,
we just won't have the resources to go
through to vet every single possible
program.
And so we're using the fact that they
have already been vetted.
For example, in Oregon,
they have to actually get approved not
just by their health department,
but also by their higher education
department.
And so they've already gone through that
kind of a review process.
And So what we're saying is we're saying
if it's gone through that type of process,
through those types of regulatory
agencies,
we will accept that as a reciprocal
requirement because that's very similar
to what we do with the,
if you've been reading in the news about
the various healthcare compacts,
that's very similar with what we do there
for other programs.
We are going to be setting up the
requirements that they have.
They'll be applications that will be out
there for programs to apply to.
But we're not going to be able,
there's just not the resources and
ability to say somebody got a
certification from this program that has
not been approved by one of the other
states.
We are not at that point going to be able
to say here we can do this now we can say
we would set up potentially a review of
those requirements and they would need to
meet the requirements New Mexico sets up.
And we could do that, you know on that.
But realize that will take a lot of time
and resources.
And I'm not sure that we would be able to
do so in a in a reasonable fashion
because there are a lot of programs out
there that offer training and it may or
may not be as extensive as some of the
other programs,
but they haven't necessarily been
reviewed.
And so we have to ensure there is that
review process.
I hope that makes sense.
Yeah, Yeah, I just, like I said,
I would hate to find out that, you know,
six months of training I went through and
paid.
I didn't.
It wasn't $10,
000 like was mentioned earlier,
but it wasn't cheap that, you know,
but if I guess with anything,
it's buyer beware, right?
I, I, if I did,
I did my due diligence or didn't do my
due diligence and find out that, you know,
you guys aren't going to accept it,
that's on me.
But I,
I do appreciate that these conversations
are going on and I very much appreciate
the discussion around how important
integration is in the,
in the speaker earlier.
It's just I have so much gratitude for
what's going on right now, guys.
It's just unbelievable.
Unbelievable.
You know,
that this has come where this where this
nation has came in the last year or two
regarding psychedelics is astonishing.
Much respect, guys.
Thank you.
Thank you, Shane.
Well,
for the sake of some of the chats are are
fairly redundant because I think we've
answered quite a bit.
So what I will do is I'll I'll go in and
select some that were, you know,
that weren't answered yet.
But in the meantime,
we could take another,
another hand phrase and and I'll then
I'll jump back to the chat here.
All right,
next we've got Deb Thorne and Deb,
I've enabled your mic.
You can unmute when you're ready.
Hello, hello.
It's great to be here.
Really good topic today.
And I did have a few questions.
I already put them in the chat but I know
it was pretty lengthy so I wanted to just
voice it.
For those of you that don't know me,
my name is Doctor Deb Thorn and I'm the
founder and Medical Director of SOLTRIP
and Clinical Director of Medicina del Sol
in Las Cruces.
I guess the thing I'm I wanted to know
more than with Catherine's presentation,
I wanted to know is psilocybin outside of
the medical program already descheduled
for training purposes,
Especially for those of us waiting to
offer this in a legal way.
Can anyone answer that?
Hi, Deb, this is Dominic.
At at this point in time,
it has not been descheduled.
And so while people are talking about
that,
that is not something that unless
somebody becomes a patient in the program,
they would not be able legally to go
through that process in New Mexico at
this time.
OK.
So I'm just curious how so many programs
that are now involved with the medical
program are able to provide that
experiential part.
How is that being done legally?
So, Deb,
right now the program does not have any
permits, licenses or anything else,
not even set up on regulation.
So we do not have the ability to.
And we don't have law enforcement
abilities, for example,
to move forward with regard to people who
are who may be utilizing illicitly.
And what we have said before in other
meetings, I've said it in interviews,
is that if individuals feel that things
are happening illicitly,
they should be reporting it to law
enforcement.
That is the same process, by the way,
that occurred when,
when medical cannabis first became legal.
The department did not have the ability
to turn around and arrest or do any of
that sort of thing if someone was
utilizing illicitly.
We stay on the side of as the medical
program gets gets set up,
how do we help and facilitate with regard
to with regard to the medication within
the program itself.
And so if somebody feels that somebody is
doing something illicit that is actually
between them and their licensing board
and or law enforcement,
that's not something that we as a program
can do.
We only have authority over those who
will be at the time when they are
actually licensed or permitted.
So if someone has been practicing in a
way that well what we call the
underground and they do apply to the
program, would they be accepted?
That needs to be determined.
And currently right now we don't,
we're not even at the point where we have
those regulations.
However it could be problematic if
somebody has any kind of criminal history
or anything else because those are going
to be some of the details that the
different committees actually are going
to have to determine.
Will that be allowed for individuals who
are then permitted to do this practice?
For example,
when medical cannabis first started and
with the producers,
individuals who had a criminal record and
had arrests and or charges,
we're not actually allowed to be able to
be cultivators,
distributors in the very beginning of the
program.
And so that's something however that was
not addressed in the statute.
And as we move forward with the
regulations,
it is one of the items that needs to be
addressed.
We just have not gotten there yet.
OK, well,
I'm glad to know that that is on the
docket and that it will be, you know,
I guess thoroughly discussed and put in
place when the time comes.
But, and and I am in no way, you know,
putting down the underground.
There are some incredible facilitators
out there and have been for decades.
And,
but a lot of them did receive a lot of
mentorship and I think that's a big part
of the training.
And, and, you know,
just harm reduction is so, so important.
So with our medical program,
I think that is definitely an order.
And, you know,
those are things that we're definitely
going to cover.
And I'm I'm happy to see that.
But yeah, I just, I wondered if you know,
for training purposes,
let's say there is a group that's
offering training for facilitators and
prescribers,
would there be allowances for those
participants in the state of New Mexico
to receive an experiential so they don't
have to go to Oregon or Colorado to
receive that?
It's a great, it's a great question, Deb.
And currently with the way the law is
currently written, we have,
we do have our legal team who is actually
looking at that because from the plain
language of the law,
it does not seem to allow it again
without somebody actually having one of
the diagnosis.
And so that is a good question.
And it may be something that in the
beginning of the program we're not able
to offer, but perhaps down the road.
So if if training program wanted to offer
that,
would we just submit something to DoH to
see if we get approval?
Well, again,
right now we haven't even set up the
requirements for those applications.
So I can't really answer that until those
are set up.
OK.
All right.
Thank you for answering those questions.
Of course.
Thank you, Deb.
Those are yeah, those are great,
great questions.
And again, you know, caution, you know,
as as far as the,
the medical cannabis goes,
there there were many,
many people who were growing and,
and supplying many people underground.
And as that started to develop,
more growers came forward and started
growing just as things started become
legalized for, for medical use.
So again, you know,
looking at the how the medical cannabis
program started off it, it's,
it's not as cut and dry as we all think
it would be.
But there are definitely, you know,
there's micrologists that are know how to
grow mushrooms And that's that was from,
you know, the propagation committee And,
you know,
so there's a lot of things that in the
meantime,
everybody has to obey the law and, and,
and go with that.
So these are really good, good questions.
So I just wanted to see if there was
anything else in the chat here that has
not been answered.
Jed.
OK,
here's 1 Ellen who is covering their
liability insurance.
So that that has come up quite a bit in
other in other meetings and meetings that
I've had.
Right now, you know,
clinicians and other specialists do have
insurance,
but right now to specialize in getting
covered for psilocybin that has not been
that has not been approached yet.
It's, it's just like anything else.
If you know,
if you're doing something nefarious with
your license,
you could potentially have that pulled if
if your,
your insurance company you've been doing
something illegally or if you've been
doing harm for that matter.
So I just wanted to answered that
question.
There's another question by Tay Davey
Davis.
How and how have people been doing this,
doing it for years?
It's it's very interesting.
Oh, I wanted to read first of all,
let me back up here.
Yeah,
I think the question there is more like,
yeah, we're,
we're just really sticking to the medical
model here and not really looking at what
other people have been doing for,
for underground for years.
So we really need to stick to that topic.
I I can't answer that.
People have been doing this for years on
their own or treating others.
That's a whole another can of worms to go
through.
There's an anyone else?
OK,
who's next to be for a question with a
raised hand here?
Next we've got James Brand and James,
I've enabled your mic and and James,
just before you start,
I do want to do a time check.
We do only have 5 minutes remaining in
the meeting,
so I know there's a couple of people with
their hands up.
If you can please make it brief and just
so we can still end on time.
Thank you again.
No problem.
Dominic and Brenda,
thank you for sharing this and great
presentation.
Catherine,
thank you so much for the information.
Everything you shared.
One comment is just that I put in the the
comments.
There is personal bias.
I think we definitely need a section on
personal bias of the facilitator to make
people aware of that while you're sitting
in that space in that container.
Thank you so much.
Thank you, James.
OK, from just to save some time,
let's attend to the raised hands at this
moment.
And I apologize we didn't get to all the
the questions in the chat.
OK, who's next?
So I, I think I'm next, I,
I came just a little bit late and it
looked like we were going over like a
supplemental course that New Mexico used.
Is that something that's already been
decided by this committee or are we going
to get a chance to kind of review that?
And if so,
or will it be sent out with the next
invitation for the next committee?
Good question, Chris.
I think we're still trying to figure that
that out.
How many hours for reciprocity and how
many hours for a full program?
So I think we're going to discuss that
even more.
So maybe next.
Next meeting.
Who's next?
With a raised hand.
All right.
Yeah.
Last, we've got desba.
And desba, I've enabled your mic.
Yep.
Hi.
Can you hear me?
Yeah.
OK.
Just really quickly,
just for the sake of definitions and for
the sake of the DoH recommendations and
medical psilocybin,
I believe that we are only working with
medical dosages and not we're working
with what are considered microdosing
because I know that that kind of came up
in, in, in one of the comments.
These are for dosages for for sitting,
not for micro doses,
not for not for that use,
not for recreational use.
It's medical psilocybin only.
Thank you.
Great presentations.
Correct that that's correct as but thank
you for mentioning that.
OK,
I think this we're we got 2 minutes left.
So thank you all for coming and sharing.
This was really a very good meeting and
your input is vital to helping us make
decisions for the Department of Health
for psilocybin medical use.
I think you know,
in the next meeting we'll have possibly
another presenter.
I'm I'm not sure yet haven't across that
Bridget.
So thank you all for coming and thank you
all for participating this and I do
apologize letting get to everyone in the
chat for questions.
Thank you and thank you everybody.
Hope you all have a great Friday and
weekend.
We'll see you all again soon.